GORDON: Previously on Gotham...
PENGUIN: You paid off the
mayor to make Jim Gordon captain.
- Don't ever betray me again.
- Never.
I need to know what Sofia is
planning and who she is planning it with.
Plain, dumb, Ed.
I would like you to
go to The Narrows
and bundle him up and
bring him back to me.
They're the ones
that are the problem.
They work for Penguin.
I would like to announce that
we just quit working for Penguin.
This is your turf now.
SOFIA: What is he doing to them?
GORDON: He 's cooking them.
They're people pies.
Eat the pies or the boy dies.
SOFIA: No!
Jim!
GORDON: The suspect
known as the Pyg is in custody.
The GCPD kept its promise.
I'm not your enemy, Jim.
I never will be.
MAN: Did you find anything out?
She will answer
for what she's done.
(DISTORTED MUSIC
PLAYING ON PHONOGRAPH)
PRISONER: Thursday.
Thursday's my day.
(PRISONER CONTINUES CHATTERING)
(MUSIC STOPS)
(OPERATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
I don't like that song.
My ma used to beat me to it.
It was playing
when I killed her.
(CHUCKLES)
So now you turn it off.
Or I do the same to you.
Why did your mother beat you?
Were you a naughty boy?
Did you soil your trousers?
(MOCKS STUTTERING)
Stutter,
perhaps?
- (GRUNTS)
- (GROANS)
Open the gate.
Open the gate, now.
All right, everybody calm down.
(GUARDS CHATTERING)
GUARD: Back off, just back off.
I really wish you
hadn't done that.
(GROANS)
I paid a fortune
to look this good.
(YELLING)
(LAUGHING)
- (GROANING)
- (OPERATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
(ALARM RINGING)
(GUARDS SHOUTING)
GUARD: Everybody,
stay where you are.
All right, open the
gate, that's enough.
Okay, it's over. Just
open the gate and let us in.
LUCIUS: The doctors at
Arkham took these after the fight.
The Pyg had titanium plates
surgically grafted onto
the bones of his face,
the result of which, radically
changed his appearance.
When we booked him, his
fingerprints were burned off.
I've seen it before on criminals
that want to hide their identity.
But never anything like this.
That's not all. The doctors
also noticed scar tissue
behind his ears and
along his neckline,
indicating he's had
multiple surgeries.
That explains why we
couldn't ID him off his photo.
This doesn't make any sense.
The Pyg is a glory hound.
Everything he's done, it's all
been about grabbing the spotlight.
Classic sociopath behavior.
So why doesn't he want
us to know who he really is?
Now is the time he should
be taking credit for his crimes.
Can you use this x-ray
to reconstruct his face?
See what he looked like
before he had any work done?
It's certainly possible,
but it'll take some time.
Get started.
I wanna know who
the Pyg really is.
- Morning, Cap.
- Harper.
How's the shoulder?
This? Just a scratch.
You got a visitor.
Thanks.
Sofia, what are you doing here?
I haven't heard from
you in a few days.
I didn't realize I
was supposed to call.
I figured after the other night,
we were gonna start
seeing each other again.
We're not.
I get it.
You're worried about
Penguin finding out about us,
that I made you Captain.
You don't have to be.
I already told him.
I'm sorry, you did what?
I have it under control.
Is that what you think?
It's what I know.
I am going to remove
Penguin from the picture,
and when I do, I
want us to be together.
It's not gonna work, Sofia.
Even if Penguin
is out of the picture.
I just don't see a way
forward for us. I'm sorry.
(PEOPLE ARGUING)
WOMAN: I run the dog
races, he runs the cock fights.
Now he's coming and
muscling in on my business.
- I got mouths to feed.
- You race those dogs again
and I'll slit your damn throat.
All right. Enough.
If she stabs him,
it solves the issue.
I started this court, so we could
work out disputes peacefully.
This is how things are gonna be
done from now on, understood?
Now you're both admitting
to having down months.
Seems the only solution
is for you to partner up.
Both of you work
together, you stay strong.
Okay. That's settled.
Thank you. Moving on. Next.
LEE: Wait.
How's your daughter?
Fever came down,
thanks to you, Doc.
Good.
These bums are
so lucky to have you.
You cure their children,
you solve their problems.
I haven't forgotten
about you, Ed.
Yes, you say that and
yet I remain a moron.
I said I would
fix you, and I will.
MAN: Out of my way.
Move out of my way.
Out of my way, I
need to see the Doc.
What happened?
Sampson sent his thugs to my
shop, demanding protection money.
I told them no.
I said, this is your
neighborhood now.
I'm sorry, who's Sampson?
He controls the territory
just south of here.
All right. Go to the
clinic, I'll stitch you up.
You know, this was
bound to happen.
You're new leader
of The Narrows.
Sampson's just testing you.
But you have to show
him, and these people,
that you can't be pushed around.
What, should I send
Grundy to rip his arms off?
Look at him, it's
what he lives for.
I'm asking these people
to settle things amicably.
I can't just be a hypocrite and send
Grundy every time I have a problem.
(SIGHS)
Okay, what would you like to do?
Hello, Sofia.
(STAMMERS)
Oswald, what a
pleasant surprise.
Oh, I assure you, dear,
there is nothing
pleasant about it.
I've continually been
suspicious of you.
And yet, at every turn,
you always had the
perfect explanation
to put my mind at ease.
But now,
I finally have proof
that you are my enemy.
You lied to me.
You told me you hated Gordon.
You are his lover.
Martin saw you kissing
him after the party.
That's ridiculous.
I'm not sure what
Martin thought he saw,
but I can assure
you it was no kiss...
Enough of your lies!
Our entire friendship,
the intimacies we shared,
they were nothing more
than a pathetic charade.
No, Oswald, I swear. I
swear, I care for you deeply...
Ha! Oh, I wish that were true!
But after Martin told me
about you and Gordon,
I did a little digging
into your boyfriend.
Interesting. He took
a trip down south
shortly before you
arrived in Gotham.
Coincidence? I think not.
So you see, I know
that the two of you
have been plotting
to destroy me from
the very beginning.
Bravo, Oswald.
Do you know, I was warned
you were a mastermind?
Turns out you're an easy mark.
It is truly amazing,
what you can accomplish
with goulash and
a good foot rub.
Now I see the real you.
(SNIFFLES)
I was blind to
your manipulations.
But today, I'm going
to correct that mistake.
You will tell me the
full extent of your plan,
if your father was involved,
which of my captains
you have turned
and how you intend
to rid me from this city.
Bring him out.
Allow me to introduce
you to the dentist.
And he is not the kind
who gives out lollipops
after the visit.
(DOOR BUZZES)
Captain Gordon.
I wondered if my little scuffle would
bring you here. I'm so glad it did.
- I've missed our little chats.
- Good.
Then you can start by
telling me who you really are.
Don't you know?
Jim, I'm a reflection of you.
I don't see it.
(THE PYG CHUCKLING)
Oh, James, you swine.
(GROANS)
I want to know who's
hiding behind that mask.
What you see is what you get.
What I see is someone
who craves attention.
So why are you concealing
your true identity?
Don't you wanna take the
credit for all your brilliant crimes?
Oh, I get all the credit.
The whole town has gone
hog wild for the Pyg. (SNORTS)
Not since I caught you.
You're yesterday's news.
- It's not true.
- This is Gotham.
You're a second-class psychopath
compared to what we've got.
Jerome Valeska,
Fish Mooney, Penguin.
- They have staying power, you don't.
- You're wrong.
I terrified this whole
city for months.
- People will remember that.
- No, they won't.
In fact, they've
already forgotten you.
Hmm, but not you,
Jim. You're here.
A final visit.
Now I'm gonna walk out that door
and never think about you again.
(CHUCKLING) Mind games.
You really think that's
going to work on me?
Guard, we're done here.
James, we're not done here.
Have a nice life.
(IN SOUTHERN ACCENT)
Don't you walk out on me!
You'll never forget me.
I promise you that.
There you are.
(DOOR LOCKS)
(GUN COCKING)
So, you're Doc?
I heard you had a giant.
I figured you might have
brought him along with you,
rather than this, uh, has-been.
Excuse me.
Why would I bring Grundy
along for a friendly conversation?
Look, I understand you
had a deal with Cherry,
where you left her people alone.
I expect you to honor
the same with me.
Why would I do that?
You'e not even from The Narrows.
You have no idea how
things work around here.
Maybe you're right.
But I do know that
you love money.
I'm willing to offer
you 10% of fight night.
You just don't get it, huh?
I'm not negotiating.
I'm taking.
I'm taking your clinic.
I'm taking your club.
I'm taking your whole
damn neighborhood.
Okay, we tried this your
way. Let's use Grundy.
(COUGHING)
That doesn't sound so good.
You cough up blood yet?
What's it to you?
Bad case of Narrows
Lung going around.
What the hell is that?
It's a new virus.
I've seen it kill a
few people already.
First you cough up blood and
within a few days you're dead.
Unless you have treatment.
I'll sweeten the deal. I will
doctor your people, free of charge.
(LAUGHING)
Not gonna get a
better offer than that.
(LAUGHING TURNS TO COUGHING)
All right.
I'll be back in a few days
to negotiate with
whoever takes your place,
after you drown
in your own blood.
Tell you what, Doc.
Make it 30% of fight night,
you got yourself a deal.
It's too much, don't take it.
(COUGHING)
Come by the clinic later.
We'll see about that cough.
(GROANING)
Your teeth are quite lovely.
I look forward to putting
them in my trophy case.
You have no idea
who I am, do you?
Of course, I do.
You are Don Falcone's daughter.
He killed my brother.
(WHIRRING)
I'm going to enjoy this.
SOFIA: It's true he
killed your brother,
but not your wife, Elaine,
or your son, Joseph.
No, they're still alive,
probably having lunch
in your two-bedroom
on 7th Ave right now.
(WHIRRING STOPS)
See, I made it a point
to learn every detail
of Penguin's organization.
For instance, I learned that he only
trusts one man for this type of job.
You.
And in the event that
I am ever tortured,
my people have instructions
to kill your family.
Interesting threat.
But no one's going to
know that you were tortured.
Because no one is
going to find your body.
Oh! 'Cause you don't think I have
spies inside Penguin's organization?
He's right about me, though.
I have been conspiring
against him for months,
turning his captains
against him one by one.
And today is the day that
I will finally take him down.
So, if my people don't
hear from me soon,
your family's dead.
But if you don't believe me,
drill away.
Excuse me,
her restraints need tightening.
- (DRILL WHIRRING)
- (MAN SCREAMING)
Hmm. A wise decision.
Now, untie me.
(WHIMPERING)
Things are finally looking up.
- BARBARA: Wakey, wakey.
- (GASPS)
Oh, hello.
I don't believe we've
met. I'm Barbara Kean.
This ferocious lady
is Tabitha Galavan
and that kitty cat,
that's Selina Kyle.
I know who you are.
Penguin wants you dead for
betraying him down in The Narrows.
What do you want with me?
Well, we heard you
and Ozzy are BFFs.
So, you're going to try and leverage
me to get Penguin not to kill you.
TABITHA: We have
some other demands.
But essentially, yeah.
That's a good plan,
except for the fact that
Penguin just tried to kill me.
Why would he do that?
Because I am so close to
taking his underworld from him.
(SELINA SCOFFS)
You're lying.
SOFIA: Am I?
I've been working
Penguin for months,
manipulating him into behaving
exactly how I want him to.
Every move he made
today, I orchestrated.
Now you three are
screwing things up.
So, you want him out
of your life, let me go.
(WHISPERS) Maybe
she's telling the truth.
She's a Falcone.
She learned to lie
before she could read.
But whether you are friend or
foe makes no difference to me,
because Penguin
will still make the deal.
Get him on the phone.
You'll grow into it.
(PENGUIN LAUGHS)
Because of you, I was
able to vanquish my enemy.
And now that you've
proven yourself,
I see a beautiful
future ahead for you.
I have so much wisdom to impart.
And if you pay attention,
one day all of this
could be yours.
What's wrong?
What are you talking about?
You mean, you did not
see Sofia kissing Gordon?
Why would she do that?
Unless...
She knew exactly
how I would respond.
She wanted me to confront her.
Even torture her.
Boss, we have a problem.
The dentist is gone.
What happened to Sofia?
To be honest, that's
still a little unclear.
Barbara Kean has her.
What? How do you know this?
She's on the phone.
Says she wants to make a deal.
Give me that.
Barbara.
Hello, Oswald.
I see you have crawled out from
whatever rock you were hiding under.
What are you doing with Sofia?
We scooped her up this morning.
And of course, when we did, we
thought she was your best friend.
Turns out, she's
your worst enemy.
I want her back.
Name your price.
We keep the gun shop,
we don't share profits
and from this point forward we
operate with complete autonomy.
Fine.
I will send Zsasz
over to collect her.
She had better be
there when he arrives.
She will be.
And as for you, young man,
our conversation is not over.
GORDON: So, this is what
the Pyg used to look like?
That's him.
All right, send it out to police
stations across the country.
- Start in the South.
- The South? Why?
When I pressed him, he
spoke in a Southern accent.
He could have done that
deliberately to throw you off.
No, he slipped up.
I saw it in his eyes.
This is the best lead we've got.
Let's see where it goes.
NYGMA: I don't understand you.
If Sampson's cough will
kill him, why not let him die?
There's no such thing
as Narrow's Lung.
He probably just has bronchitis.
I give him some medicine,
he feels better, problem solved.
Okay, what about the 30%?
Once he has that, he's
just gonna want more.
Maybe.
Sampson, you son of a bitch.
Now do you see who
you're dealing with?
I know you wanted
to try this your way.
No more diplomacy, Lee.
Take Grundy and end this.
No.
I have a better idea.
- That was easy.
- Yeah, a little too easy.
SOFIA: Because he couldn't
wait to get you off the phone.
We need to get out of here.
And then what happens?
You take over from Penguin?
We are not working for
anyone but ourselves.
I'm not asking you to.
I will give you everything
you want from Penguin.
You're not in a position
to offer us anything.
We're in charge here.
Uh, guys, I think we
should listen to her.
Why?
Because Zsasz is standing out
front holding a rocket launcher.
Ladies.
(LAUGHING)
(ALL COUGHING)
I'm gonna break
his little beak in half.
SOFIA: Jim.
Sorry, Captain. I tried to stop
her. I told her she had to wait.
It's okay,
Detective. I've got it.
Sofia, what happened to you?
I underestimated Oswald.
He found out we were
plotting against him
and he just tried
to kill me, Jim.
He can't hurt you here.
If he finds out I'm alive,
he will come after me
and he won't
stop until I'm dead.
You are the Captain of the GCPD,
your men would follow you anywhere.
Please, please, use the
position I gave you and end this.
What are you proposing I do?
You have an army, just
take the fight to Penguin.
So, this was your plan.
To start a war.
You knew you didn't have the
numbers to fight Penguin on your own,
so you made me Captain,
knowing it would come to this,
and I'd take him out for you.
Your job is to stop
criminals, Jim, here you go.
It is not that simple,
and you know it.
We could bring law and
order back to Gotham.
This is exactly what you asked
for when you came down south
and it is yours for the taking.
You know what
has to be done, Jim.
Crush Penguin.
I trusted you, Martin.
And you betrayed me.
I think it's time for you to
go back to the orphanage.
- Boss.
- Hold on.
Let the little spy
step out of the room.
So?
The place went up
like a great ball of fire.
Good. Alert the capos.
We are going to unleash a crime
wave on this city like it has never seen.
That will teach Jim Gordon
to align himself
with Sofia Falcone.
GORDON: I wouldn't
make that call if I were you.
I just spoke with Sofia.
She's alive.
And she told me
you tried to kill her.
Hearsay, Jim.
Been here all day.
I have witnesses.
I don't care.
I'm not here to arrest you.
I came to make a deal.
I think we've both put
up with Sofia long enough.
Victor, would you
give us a moment?
Okay, Jim. You
have my attention.
Since the moment
she set foot in Gotham,
Sofia has put us
on a path to war.
She's willing to let this
city burn to the ground
to prove herself to her father.
I can't allow that.
So, what do you want from me?
I'm putting her on
a train home tonight.
But I need assurances from
you, you won't get involved.
Not good enough.
She needs to suffer
for what she has done.
That is not gonna happen.
And how do you think
your girlfriend's gonna react
when she realizes
you betrayed her?
You think she's just
gonna run away quietly?
If she sets foot in Gotham
again, I'll put her behind bars.
And if I say no?
Then I'll have no choice
but to use the full
force of the GCPD
to tear you apart,
piece by piece.
That does not
sound very pleasant.
It won't be.
I guess I can put aside
my personal feelings
for the good of this city.
But I do have one
question for you, Jim.
When Sofia is gone,
where does that leave us?
No more licenses.
If you or any other criminal
in this city break the law,
my men will enforce it.
But at least you won't have
to worry about Sofia again.
So, do we have a deal?
After all we have been
through together, Jim,
it is nice that we can resolve
this matter with diplomacy.
(SAMPSON BURPING)
Doc.
I heard about what
happened to your clinic.
What a shame.
I was looking forward to
you curing my Narrows Lung.
(LAUGHING)
I want you cleared out of The
Narrows by the end of the day.
- What did you say to me?
- I think she was pretty clear.
Well, allow me to be clear.
This is my turf and
I'm not going anywhere.
And you two have
dug your own graves.
Oh, well, then I guess
you don't want this.
What's that?
The antidote to the poison
I had slipped in your
drink about 30 minutes ago.
Ironic, isn't it?
It's the only thing from the
clinic that wasn't destroyed,
some vials of medicine I had
mixed into a deadly combination.
It should be kicking
in right about now.
You're bluffing. I feel
absolutely fine. (GROANS)
I'm sorry, what was that?
Get them.
LEE: Come any closer
and I'll destroy this.
(SAMPSON COUGHING)
Like I said,
leave by the end of
the day and you live.
Deal?
Oh!
Catch.
(COUGHING INTENSIFIES)
I know you're disappointed,
but I am doing this to protect you.
Disappointment doesn't
quite cover it, Jim.
If you stay in Gotham,
Penguin will kill you.
Don't put this on Penguin.
If you have something to
say, I think you should say it.
We're the same, Jim.
I saw it the first
moment we met.
We both want power.
You want to deny
it, but it's true.
And it is just easier
to send me away.
(HANDCUFFS CLICKING)
Detective Harper, please take
Miss Falcone to the train station
and escort her back home.
Please, don't do this.
Better get going.
You'll miss your train.
(THUNDER RUMBLING)
ZSASZ: Gordon
put her on the train.
Talk about a turn of events.
I did not see that coming.
What about the kid? You want me
to take him back to the orphanage?
That won't be necessary.
Martin, I have been thinking.
I was angry.
I did not mean what I...
Martin.
(CAR DOOR OPENING)
BARBARA: Aw!
He's cute.
He doesn't talk.
Kid gives me the creeps.
Let's get this over with.
Nervous about something?
Well, we have a long way to go.
So, get comfy.
MAN: Tickets, please.
(GASPS) What...
(GUN COCKING)
- Hello, Victor.
- Where's the boy?
Alive, for now.
If Oswald wants
to keep it that way,
he will meet me under the
Crown Point Bridge in one hour.
CONDUCTOR: (ON PA)
Next stop, Stevenstown.
It's my stop.
Do you mind?
Not at all.
Thank you.
Glad you could make it, Oswald.
Everything will be all
right, Martin, I promise.
Well, that depends on you.
Turn over control of
the underworld to me
and I'll let little Martin
here keep his head.
The name Falcone used to
mean something in this town.
Wait until your
father hears of this.
Threatening the life of a
child? He will be disgusted.
Wrong.
My father will be proud.
Must be hard to
live your whole life
trying to get Daddy's approval.
I, myself, can't relate,
seeing as my parents
loved me without condition.
Say one more word
and I will kill him
and then I will execute you.
I am choosing compassion,
but I am willing to
change my position.
Don't hurt the boy.
He's innocent.
I submit!
(WHISPERING) Go ahead.
Martin, I want you to know,
I am sorry for
what I said today.
I do care about you.
You know that's true, don't you?
Good.
Now, go wait in the car.
You were wise to use the boy.
As you know,
my heart is my
greatest weakness.
But I will not allow him
to be used as a pawn
in your game anymore.
(GASPS)
You wanted a war,
you've got one!
Ed, why so blue?
We had a great day.
You had a great day.
I did nothing to help.
That's not true.
I couldn't have
done it without you.
I'm not meant to
be a sidekick, Lee.
Sampson is right.
I'm a has-been.
No, you're not.
Look, I asked you to trust me
with something today, and you did.
So, I'm gonna trust
you with something.
I haven't been looking for
a cure for your brain, Ed,
because there's
nothing wrong with you.
- But you...
- Sure,
at first there was an
effect from the ice.
But I ran all the
tests, checks out.
There's nothing wrong
with you physically.
Your condition is psychological.
Think about it.
You knew every move that
Sampson was gonna make
before he made it.
You lied to me.
Why?
Because I was afraid
that if I told you the truth,
you would go back to
being who you were before.
The Riddler.
And I like who you've become.
Who's that?
Ed Nygma.
The Ed that you were before.
My friend.
Well, that backfired.
Penguin's gonna be coming
for us. What are we gonna do?
We hit him before he hits us.
Lady, you lost.
Penguin just blew up that kid.
I admit I didn't
see that coming.
But Oswald still has to align
his capos before he moves on us.
We use that window
of time to make our play.
You didn't get told "no"
a lot as a kid, did you?
You took your shot
and you missed.
We're going it alone from here.
You leave now,
and you will never
have a piece of this city.
Now, that sounded like a threat.
Your club is destroyed. You
have nowhere else to turn.
You need me.
Penguin may have won the battle,
but tomorrow, we win the war.
ZSASZ: Boss.
My boy,
you did a splendid job of dying.
Victor will take you
to a safe location.
You can never return to Gotham.
This is goodbye, my friend.
There, there.
This is what I have
to do to protect you.
One day, when you're
older, you will understand.
Sofia's on our heels, boss.
Let's finish her off.
Have someone else take the kid.
No! I want my top man on this.
Besides, I have something much
better planned for Sofia Falcone.
You were right about the Pyg.
A precinct down south
recognized the picture
you had me send out.
His real name is
Lazlo Valentine.
What do we know about him?
He was being held for a string of
murders down there 10 years ago.
But here's the thing.
His previous victims
weren't police officers
and there was no Pyg persona.
Serial killers don't
usually change their MO.
This guy did.
You said he was being held.
Did they say why
their case fell apart?
It didn't. He escaped.
Call Arkham. Have them
put a guard on his cell.
I'm on my way.
(METALLIC SCRAPING)
Pyg?
(SCRAPING CONTINUES)
Pyg!
(CHOKING)
(GASPS)
- Hello, Ed.
- No.
No!
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
Miss me? (LAUGHING MANIACALLY)
(THUNDER RUMBLING)
GORDON: Open it, let's go.
GUARD: Sound the alarm!
(ALARM RINGING)
English-US-Template